Today's דף daf is מ״ב Mem-Bet and we pick up at the
very top of מ״ב עמוד א׳ Mem-Bet Amud Aleph and what we
had been discussing yesterday was the statement that if you eat a
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, the תורה Torah prohibits you to eat a
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach נא ובשל מבושל. na uvashel mevushal. נא Na
was what the גמרא Gemara interpreted not as totally raw but as
like as rare, a highly undercooked or cooked as opposed to צלי
אש. tzali esh.
I do want to say that afterwards there was a discussion whether
נא na actually means the way the גמרא Gemara is interpreting it
and I did, you know, whether that's the פשט. pshat. I did
check a concordance and the concordance has, it says one of the
meanings of נא na is undercooked and but the only example in
all of תנ״ך Tanakh is this פסוק. pasuk. So but it doesn't
disagree with the way the גמרא Gemara is reading it but it
is interesting that there is no other use of the word נא
na in this context in this in this sense of a of
a type of cooking other than in this פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, or
if one ate it in any way that was even not raw
or undercooked,
let's even not rare or undercooked, let's say even not rare or
cooked, but even if it was somehow other not צלי אש, tzali
esh, that's the end of the פסוק: pasuk: כי אם צלי אש.
ki im tzali esh. Whether if it's not צלי אש tzali esh
but it's neither rare nor undercooked—I did it again—neither rare nor cooked,
is that going to be a problem of a positive מצווה? mitzvah?
Is that going to be a negative מצווה? mitzvah? Are you going
to get lashes? That was some of the issues that we discussed.
But anyway that's the prohibition and those prohibitions apply only in the
evening when it's the מצווה mitzvah to eat it and the מצווה
mitzvah is to eat it when it is צלי אש, tzali esh,
roasted. The last thing we left off of was a statement that
if somebody ate it the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach צלי אש tzali
esh but in ערב פסח Erev Pesach they transgress
and
the גמרא Gemara says it sounds like they transgress a negative prohibition
but where is there a negative prohibition? We know that there's a
positive מצווה: mitzvah: ואכלו את הבשר בלילה הזה, ve-achalu es habasar balaila
hazeh, eat it this night, but it does not, but there's nowhere
it has a negative prohibition of not to eat it earlier, so
you would negate the positive but you would not transgress the negative.
So the גמרא Gemara says so let's just pick up, that was
the question the גמרא Gemara left off with. Very last line we'll
read of מ״א עמוד ב׳: Mem-Aleph Amud Bet: אמר רב חסדא, Amar
Rav Chisda, הא מני? היא רבי יהודה. Ha mani? Hi Rebbe Yehuda.
It's
רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Baraita:
שור ושה שרוע וקלוט נדבה תעשה אתו ולנדר לא ירצה. shor vaseh
sarua ve-kalut nedavah ta'aseh oso ule-neder lo yeratzeh. That's what the פסוק
pasuk says. If you have an ox or a sheep that is
שרוע sarua or קלוט, kalut, which is a certain type of a
blemish which is according to, it's either that one of the limbs
is disfigured or that the hooves are not fully, are not fully
split, so you can make it a נדבה nedavah but not a
נדר. neder. And what does it mean you can make it a
נדבה nedavah and not a נדר? neder? According to חז״ל Chazal that
means you can donate it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash as
in terms of its, you know, monetary value for for resale and
for using the proceeds, but you can't make it into a קרבן
korban because it has a blemish. אתו אתה מתפיס לבדק הבית, Oso
atah matpis le-bedek habayis, here is the rabbinic interpretation: אתו אתה מתפיס
לבדק הבית. oso atah matpis le-bedek habayis. Now clearly then if you
sanctified an animal with a blemish for a קרבן korban you would
transgress a negative prohibition, right?
ולנדר לא ירצה. u-leneder lo yeratzeh. Okay but let's say but there's
another flip side of that, not that you cannot give a
a קרבן korban with a blemish, an animal with a blemish, as
a קרבן, korban, but here's the flip side: אתו אתה מתפיס לבדק
הבית, oso atah matpis le-bedek habayis, something with a blemish you can
donate to the house treasury, you know, for the proceeds, ואי אתה
מתפיס תמימים לבדק הבית. ve-i atah matpis temimim le-bedek habayis. So there's
a, this is the parallel: you cannot sanctify an animal with a
blemish as a קרבן korban but you can also not sanctify an
unblemished animal and donate it for its monetary value. An unblemished animal
is seen as something that, you know, if you're going to give
it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash should be used as a
קרבן korban and using it as a קרבן korban is of greater,
sort of, you know, elevation of greater purpose of that thing because
the thing itself is used in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash as
opposed to just selling it and using its proceeds. So therefore the
דרשה drasha is is that you actually transgress if you sanctify an
unblemished animal because it's
נדבה תעשה אתו, nedavah ta'aseh oso, תעשה אתו, ta'aseh oso, this type
of an animal you give as a as a donation. You don't
give an unblemished animal as a donation. Okay so just let me
read this: ואי אתה מתפיס תמימים לבדק הבית. ve-i atah matpis temimim
le-bedek habayis. מכאן אמרו Mikan amru and from this they said: המתפיס
תמימים לבדק הבית עובר בעשה. hamatpis temimim le-bedek habayis over be-aseh. Somebody
that donates an unblemished animal for the temple treasury עובר בעשה, over
be-aseh, you transgress a positive מצווה, mitzvah, which makes sense: נדבה תעשה
אתו, nedavah ta'aseh oso, this one you give as a as a
donation. So you would have transgressed what was implied by that positive
מצווה. mitzvah. The positive מצווה... mitzvah... give blemished animals as a donation
implies but not unblemished animals, so you transgress the positive mitzvah of
blemished animals are a donation. אין לי אלא בעשה, ein li ela
be'aseh, fine, that is a positive mitzvah that you would have negated.
בלא תעשה מנין, belo ta'aseh minayin, how do I know you even
transgress a negative prohibition? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, so the verse says,
וידבר השם אל משה לאמר, vaydaber Hashem el Moshe lemor, God spoke
to Moses saying, that's the beginning of this parsha by the blemished
animals. לימד על כל הפרשה כולה שתהא בלא תעשה, limed al kol
haparsha kula shetehei belo ta'aseh, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So
Rabbi Yehuda says, oh, that teaches you that the anything that you
do wrong that's implied by this parsha, you transgress a negative prohibition.
Where do you get that from?
So אמר לו רבי לבר קפרא, amar lo Rebbe leBar Kappara, מה
משמע, mai mashma, where do you get that from? From וידבר השם
אל משה לאמר vaydaber Hashem el Moshe lemor that if you do
anything that's implied to be wrong, it's you're transgressing a negative
prohibition? אמר לו דכתיב לאמר, amar lo dechtiv lemor, the word לאמר,
lemor, God spoke to Moses saying, so we're going to do a
very interesting drahsa on that word. לאמר lemor means לא נאמר בדברים
אלו, lo ne'emar bidevarim elu, לא נאמר, lo ne'emar, לאמר. lemor. So
there's a no that's being said here. So every time so right
when I say something, it means no, okay, so lo. So רבי
בי רב אמרי, Rebbe bei Rav amri, לאמר לאו אמור, lemor lav
emor, a prohibition is said. So now that means that a prohibition
is said, not of course, Tosafos says, not by anything, but things
that you know are forbidden because of a positive mitzvah, so the
introduction of וידבר השם אל משה לאמר vaydaber Hashem el Moshe lemor
tells you you also transgress a negative. Now you're right, it becomes
crazy if you try to apply that now every single time we
say don't do something because there's a positive mitzvah, you know, that
says do x, or it's implied don't do not x, you know,
according to this drahsa, if the parsha opened with וידבר השם אל
משה לאמר, vaydaber Hashem el Moshe lemor, it's actually a negative prohibition.
Say the drahsa
is
the drahsa is ל' א' lamed aleph surrounded by quotes, lo.
Right, like the aleph is like doubled. Lo emor, lemor, right.
So now as to the מום, mum, if I מקדיש makdish or
מטפיס matpis an animal with a מום mum to בדק הבית bedek
habayit and then I'm גוזז gozez for example, is that מעילה me'ilah
also?
Yes, but I don't want to talk about that now. But the
answer is yes. You transgress מעילה me'ilah whether something
is קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, is intrinsically sanctified and going to be
used itself in the Beis Hamikdash or whether it is קדושת דמים
kedushat damim and only going to be used for its proceeds. Either
way, there is
מעילה, me'ilah, yes.
But point two, it just makes me think conceptually that, you know,
you're thinking of these nice עגלות לויים agalot levi'im that the נשיאים
nesi'im donated, you know, for so they must have all had מומין,
mumin, the oxen. Otherwise it would have to be קרבנות. korbanot.
I guess so.
It's a good point. You know, the other thing is, you know,
ציצית, tzitzis, it's also לאמר, lemor, right? But that's clearly you're not
over on a.
That's a good question. I mean, yeah, you're right. Once you start
applying this, so now according to Rabbi Yehuda,
you know, if I wear a four-cornered בגד beged without ציצית, tzitzis,
not only am I מבטל עשה, mevatel aseh, I negate a לא
תעשה. lo ta'aseh. It becomes, you know, look, the implications of this
are huge. So I don't really know, you know, you know, the
Gemara assumes that he that in order to explain where's the negative
prohibition for eating the Korban Pesach the day before assumes that the
statement he made here could be applied globally. But if you apply
it globally, you're right, it gets you get a little carried away.
Oh, but that's not וידבר השם אל משה לאמר, vaydaber Hashem el
Moshe lemor, right? But it's still
לאמר. lemor. Maybe only by וידבר, vaydaber, who knows? I don't know.
Okay, לשון lashon because וידבר vaydaber is לשון קשה. lashon kasha. Anyway,
that's that. Now, last point in the Mishna from this perek. מי
תשמישו של נחתום, mi tashmisho shel nachtom, if you the end of
the Mishnayos remind you, first dealt with the eating of Matzah, Marror,
and Korban Pesach, not the whole aspect of Korban Pesach but at
least ways in which it's eaten or dipped in liquid and so
on, cooked with liquid. But there was also at the end a
couple of examples about like mixing your grain with other things to
make, you know, to use for even non-eating purposes, but animal food
and other types of things to to put on wounds, and nevertheless
the concern that it'll become chametz. So the last case was that
the water that the baker uses to dip his hands in to
wash off the, you know, sticky dough on the hands. They didn't
have running water. That stuff has to be spilled because that stuff
will get the dough and will become chametz. Okay, so the Gemara
says like this. תני חדא, tani chada, with one braisa teaches, שופכין
במקום מדרון, shofchin bemakom midron, if you spill it, you have to
spill it at a place of an incline so that it like,
you know, runs down the incline and gets absorbed in the ground
or all runs away somewhere. ואין שופכין במקום האשבורן, v'ein shofchin bemakom
ha'ishborn,
but you can't spill it on a flat level ground because if
you'd spill on a level ground, it'll like pool and it won't
all get absorbed and you'll have and you'll still have chametz right
in front of you. ותני אידך, v'tani idach, we've had another braisa,
שופכין במקום האשבורן, shofchin bemakom ha'ishborn, you can spill it on a
level ground. So the Gemara says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not
difficult. הא דנפישי דקוו הא דלא נפישי דלא קוו, ha denafishi dekavu
ha dela nafishi dela kavu, the first case, the case where you
can't do it is that there's... a lot of water so they
will sort of collect and therefore it doesn't get absorbed right away
if you spill it on level ground and if you spill it
on an incline it's running down so as it runs down the
incline it has chance to spread out and get absorbed. But if
you spill it on the level ground it'll puddle and then you'll
have the water sitting there for a while. And the other case
is that there's not a lot of water if there's not a
lot of water so you can spill it even on level ground
it'll get absorbed and you'll be fine. Again what I don't understand
is how frequently do you have to spill it? Meaning why isn't
it regularly becoming חמץ? chometz? How are you allowed to be doing
this on פסח? Pesach? I don't know the answer. אמר רב יהודה.
Amar Rav Yehuda. So Rav Yehuda said, אישה, isha, right? If we
were doing this nowadays we'd say you have to first fill the
whole barrel with soap and together with the water so any חמץ
chometz that you get in it, any dough you get in it
automatically becomes נפסל מאכילה. nifsal me'achila. I don't know, somehow the גמרא
Gemara isn't worried about the fact that what's happening to it that
it's becoming חמץ chometz before you spilled it.
Maybe it's not standing water, maybe your hand is constantly in it
and that's disrupting.
Well no your hand goes from the dough to the water and
from the dough to the water, the frequency, I don't know.
Maybe,
I really don't know.
Okay.
אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. So said Rav Yehuda, אישה, isha,
right? Because we kept talking about as we said he pointed out
the other day, it normally assumes the woman is like baking in
the house but it speaks about a baker as a professional role
as a man. But anyway, so a woman לא תלוש אלא במים
שלנו. lo telush ela bemayim shelannu. She
can only knead her dough with water that has slept over, from
the word לינה, lina, right? But מים mayim is לשון רבים, lashon
rabbim, so the water has לנו, lannu, has slept over the night
before. They were afraid that in ניסן, Nissan, in the spring, which
is when you're doing this, making your dough, baking your מצות, matzos,
the water that you get from underground is warm and warm water
is considered to be a concern that it'll speed up the fermentation,
so you have to let the water stay overnight and cool off
and then you'll be able to use it the next morning and
it'll be more like cool water.
So that's what he said, he gave that דרשה. drasha. So he
gave that פסק. psak. So דרש רב מתנה בפפוניא. Darash Rav Matna
bePappunya. So Rav Matna got up and taught this publicly in this
town called פפוניא. Pappunya. למחר, Lemachar, the next morning, אייתו כולי עלמא
חצבאיהו, aitu kulei alma chatzvayehu, everybody came, אייתו כולי עלמא חצבאיהו, aitu
kulei alma chatzvayehu, everybody brought their jugs, ואתו לגביה, ve'atu legabeih, and
they came to him. The next morning he woke up, he opened
the door and all the people were gathered around his house with
jugs in their hands. ואמרו ליה, Ve'amru leih, they said to him,
הב לן מיא, Hav lan mayya, give us your water! Why? Because
he said you can only do the מצוה, mitzvah, you can only
make מצות matzos with מים שלנו. mayim shelannu. So they all thought
he meant with our water! Our! So he said if you want
to make מצות, matzos, you got to use our water. So they
all came to him the next morning and said give us your
water!
So he said, this has got to be one of the funniest
puns in the גמרא. Gemara. So anyway, אמר להו, Amar lehu, he
said back to them, אנא במיא דביתו אמרי. Ana bemayya d'veitu amri.
No, so he translated it into Aramaic from the Hebrew. I meant
water that slept, I didn't mean our water. Okay so you mean
like
blessed by the rabbi or something?
Yes, something like that. Water blessed by the rabbi, he should have
charged a premium for it. Rabba water.
I mean it was that this לימוד limmud based on this pun
was brought to compromise the נאמר ne'emar דרשה drasha that immediately preceded
it.
What do you mean?
Well it's the same rhetorical
structure, נאמר לא אמור, ne'emar lo emor, לאמור לא
נאמר, lemor lo ne'emar, שלנו
שלנו.
shelannu shelannu. To me it resonated as a
similar idea and it
neutralizes the impact of that דרשה. drasha. Interesting read.
Interesting read. Okay. So it says, alright. So that's cool water with
a very interesting and funny punny story. So anyway, דרש רבא. Darash
Rava. So Rava said, now that we said about a woman only
using water that slept, אישה לא תלוש בחמה. Isha lo telush bachama.
So similar idea of a concern about the water being hot, she
should not knead her bread out in the sunlight because the sun
will heat up the water that she's using. Remember they're not getting
their water coming from a running pipe and whatever. They have a
barrel filled with water. If you're out in the sun the water
in the barrel is heating up. ולא בחמי חמה, Velo bechamei chama,
and certainly not in water that's already been heated by the sun,
let alone been heated by fire. It might not be called מבושל
mevushal as we discussed yesterday, but it's still warm water and will
speed up the חמץ chometz process. ולא במים הגרופים מן המוליאר, Velo
bemayim hagrufim min hamulyar, and not from water that is left over
at the bottom of a מוליאר mulyar which is like a metal
cooking pot. So even if it's been sitting off the fire the
metal retains the heat of the fire and the water that's sitting
on the bottom is going to also be hot. ולא, Velo, so
that's all the same basic point that the water has to be
cool, ולא תגביה ידה מן התנור עד שתגמור את כל הפת. velo
tagbiya yadah min hatannur ad shetigmor et kol hapat. She cannot lift
her hand from the oven until she finishes all the bread, all
the loaf. She cannot lift her hand from the oven. until all
the bread is finished, which basically means she has to constantly be
working the dough until it goes into the oven, because if you're
constantly working the dough you don't give it a chance to become
חמץ. chametz. וצריכה V'tzricha as opposed to וצריך V'tzarich because we're talking
about a woman, שני כלים shnei keilim and when she's making the
dough, she needs two barrels or two vessels. אחד שמקטפת בו Echad
shemekatefet bo ואחד שמצננת בו את ידיה. v'echad shemetzanenet bo et yadeha.
One that she uses to actually, you know, like slap the dough,
to roll the dough, and the other that she actually cools off
her hand, because, you know, you're beating the dough and pounding it
and all of that and your hands get hot. So now the
rinsing of the hands is not just a concern of, you know,
they're sticky and whatever and a hygiene or a cleanliness concern, the
concern of the heat of the hands is that as your hands
get hotter, right, then we've got a problem of too much heat
around, and we therefore want you to cool off your hands, so
you need a pot that you actually, something you dip your hands
in to cool off in between, you know, in between the lumps
of dough.
Is this on פסח Pesach or preparing?
Well, this would be, I mean, either way. Why do you, why
would you think there'd be a difference?
No, I'm just, I don't know, because like, say, I get, yeah,
okay.
I mean, the problem as we pointed out is if it's on
פסח, Pesach, what are you doing with the cleaning water that's becoming
חמץ, chametz, you know? And again, the משנה mishnah just said spill
it out, but it wasn't worried about that. So, but here the
משנה mishnah just sort of assumed you were using it because, you
know, you got to wash your hands every now and then. Here
we're saying actually, no, you got to do something like this to
keep your hands cool. Yeah.
My question is, you know, so when do you say the modern
technology obviates some of these problems? Like let's say I just turn
on the faucet, the cold water and I need it, or just
refrigerated it, maybe even the dough,
or have air conditioning going
on or whatever.
So, I mean, everyone always does this, at least you go to
Chabad they really specifically take מים שלנו. mayim shelanu. I mean, what
about all the other matzah bakeries? I mean, do we really care
about this anymore? Do we have to? Yeah, but do we have
to?
I mean, logically you shouldn't. All of these are not sort of
ritual concerns, they're just reality concerns about heat or whatever and could
be addressed in other ways, right? The fact that people, you know,
sort of sanctify every little part of the process is not a
חידוש. chidush. But I'd have to get back to you to see
like how much that's actually been like explicitly פסק'נד paskened or whatnot,
but logically, no, you shouldn't have to.
But some of this, even in ancient water gathering situations, well water
is cold, river water is cold, if you let it sit it
warms up. I mean, where does it get hot?
רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi says underground wells, I mean he says
that it's in the spring. I mean the גמרא Gemara says it
elsewhere as well. Sun goes under the earth, do you believe that?
Yeah, right, although that was, right, that was like the end of
the, yeah, right, it was the beginning of the spring, it was
the end of the winter, that's, you know, but it doesn't matter
what explanation they gave for it, they were responding to a phenomenon
that they had observed, which was that the spring, you know, wells
from underneath the ground, the water was hot during the
wintertime. I have no idea. If Charlie was here, he'd go find
out the answer from Wikipedia.
But with respect to somebody asked that, right?
No, but the גמרא Gemara clearly in other places makes that observation.
Maybe they knew about מים שלנו mayim shelanu and they thought they
meant... Maybe. The גמרא Gemara clearly makes that observation elsewhere that in
the winter the well water is warm from under the ground. I
don't know what to say about that. Okay. איבעיא להו, Ibayahu, they
asked the question: עברה ולשה מהו? Avra v'lasha mahu? Let's say a
woman actually transgressed and used warm water
in the kneading of the dough. Would we say that it is,
that בדיעבד b'diavad it's okay or not? Or like as we've learned
before, you know, you can look at the dough and you can
actually observe it and see if it became חמץ. chametz. So maybe
that would be okay if בדיעבד b'diavad she actually did this. מהו?
Mahu? So
מר זוטרא אמר מותר, Mar Zutra amra mutar, Mar Zutra said permissible.
רב אשי אמר אסור, Rav Ashi amar assur, no, if she did
it, בדיעבד b'diavad it's going to remain forbidden. אמר מר זוטרא, Amar
Mar Zutra, Mar Zutra said: מנא מינא לה, Mina mina la, where
do I get this from? דתניא, De-tania, we taught in the ברייתא
braita two days ago: אין לשין את השעורים בפסח, Ein loshin et
haseorim b'pesach, you do not remove the bran from the barley on
פסח Pesach with the use of water. ואם לתתה, V'im latata, and
if you did it,
נתבקעו אסורין, nitbaku asurin, if the kernels cracked it's forbidden, לא נתבקעו
מותרין, lo nitbaku mutarin, if not they're permissible. So you see even
when we say don't do something, you can still if you went
ahead and did it, you can still by observation afterwards determine whether
or not it became חמץ, chametz, and if it's not חמץ chametz
you're okay. So if that's true there, it should be true here
and you look at the dough like we, and we know that
you can look at the dough and make that observation. ורב
אשי אמר, V'Rav Ashi amar, so Rav Ashi said: אטו, Atu, what
are you talking about?
כולה חדא מחיסתא מחיסתינהו, Kulla chada machista machistinhu, were they all taught
in one bundle? Meaning just because in one case we say בדיעבד
b'diavad it's okay, doesn't mean that it's true in all cases. היכא
דאיתמר איתמר והיכא דלא איתמר לא איתמר, Heicha d'itmar itmar v'heicha d'lo
itmar lo itmar, when it was said it was said, when it
wasn't said it wasn't said. So there we say בדיעבד b'diavad it's
okay, here we don't. Now, interestingly, why בדיעבד bedi'avad would it not
be okay? The logical thing we would assume would be the גמרא
Gemara would be saying you can't always trust observation, but רש"י Rashi
says that's not true, because you might remember a few days ago
we said you can even buy what from non-Jews to make your
מצה matzah from? I mean, not your מצה matzah of מצווה, mitzvah,
but to make מצה matzah you can eat on פסח, Pesach, what?
Dough. Even so, if they've already turned it into dough, you haven't
been observing what type of water they used, you haven't been observing
a lot of things in the process. But you can look at
it now and see that it has not begun to become חמץ.
chametz. So רש"י Rashi said there is no question that observation tells
you the answer whether it's been חמץ chametz or not. But when
the גמרא Gemara says here בדיעבד bedi'avad it's אסור, assur, it means
because you disregarded
the rabbinic rule. The rabbis told you not to use warm water.
So if you disregarded it, then according to at least this opinion,
we might say there are consequences to you having disregarded it. Not
because it actually became חמץ. chametz. You could tell it's not חמץ.
chametz. We admit that. And if you bought it from non-Jews, that
would be fine. But if you disregarded the rules we said, maybe
there are going to have to be consequences. That's the way רש"י
Rashi understands that opinion, which is important because it again underscores that
we really can, at least the גמרא, Gemara, we never do this
nowadays, but at least in the גמרא Gemara they really thought, understood
that by observation you could determine whether something has become חמץ chametz
or not. Okay. הדרן עלך כל שעה. Hadran alach Kol Sha'ah. That
is the end of the second פרק. perek. We now enter the
third פרק, perek, which is the last פרק perek that deals with
issues of חמץ. chametz. And I should say of חמץ chametz and
of מצה matzah in the sense of, not the actual speaking about
the eating at the night, but the object of the מצה matzah
and what is needed to be כשר kosher מצה. matzah. So we
have one more פרק perek around חמץ, chametz, and then we turn
into other things and there'll be a major section about the קרבן
פסח korban Pesach before we get to the tenth פרק, perek, which
is about the סדר Seder night. So let's take a look now
at this third and final פרק perek devoted to issues primarily around
חמץ. chametz. ואלו עוברין בפסח. V'eilu ovrin b'Pesach. The following
things, I'm going to give another meaning in a minute, but for
now I will read this: the following things you transgress on פסח.
Pesach. כותח הבבלי, Kutach ha'Bavli, Babylonian כותח, kutach, which is a type
of a מילכיק milchic dip that has in it sour milk and
also molded bread, ושכר המדי, v'sheichar ha'Madi, and Median beer or
mead, which used barley
because some types of these things didn't use barley, they used date
honey or something, but this used barley, the Median version, וחומץ האדומי,
v'chometz ha'Adomi, Edomian vinegar, because as we mentioned the other days normal
vinegar is with wine, but this actually had a basis with barley
or grain,
וזיתום המצרי, v'zeisom ha'Mitzri, Egyptian זיתום, zeisom, which is some type of
a dip or some again, we'll find out.
Is it an olive dip of some sort?
Because זית? zayit? No, I don't think so. I don't think the
גמרא Gemara says the ingredients. I do not think olive oil is
there or olives.
וזומן של צבעים, v'zoman shel tzavai'im, some type of a plaster, but
dye or mix for dyers, or it's used in the process of
dyeing, D-Y, not D-I whatever, dyeing, ועמילן של טבחים, v'amilan shel tabachim,
and
also some type of a dough used by butchers, which
is put on the pots
that are cooking to absorb some of the froth, וקולן של סופרים,
v'kolan shel sofrim, and the glue of scribes. Okay now, so these
are things that are not straight חמץ, chametz, but nevertheless you transgress.
Now I'll in a minute talk about them. Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר,
Rabbi Eliezer omer, אף תכשיטי נשים, af tachshitei nashim, even ornaments of
women, which basically means makeup for women's makeup that obviously has some
grain component, a flour component. זה הכלל, Ze ha'klal, this is the
principle. כל שהוא ממין דגן, Kol she'hu mi'min dagan, anything that has
some type of a flour component, a grain component, הרי זה עובר
בפסח. harei ze over b'Pesach. You transgress on פסח. Pesach. הרי אלו
באזהרה, Harei eilu b'azhara, there's a negative prohibition, ואין בו משום כרת,
v'ein bo mishum kares, but it's not full חמץ chametz that if
you would eat it you would get כרת. kares. Now we have
to discuss two things here. What is the difference between עובר, over,
what does עובר over mean as opposed to the last line? The
last line is a negative prohibition but you don't get כרת. kares.
Now what is the only thing you get כרת kares for relating
to חמץ chametz on פסח? Pesach? If you do what with the
חמץ? chametz? Eat it. If you eat it. So the last line
that says הרי אלו באזהרה, Harei eilu b'azhara, there's a negative prohibition
but there's no כרת, kares, means that if you eat it you
still transgress,
but because for some reason it's not full חמץ, chametz, which I'll
discuss why in a minute, you don't get כרת. kares. כרת Kares
is only full כרת, kares, but this is somehow not full, like
it's sort of like blood. דם הנפש Dam ha'nefesh you get כרת,
kares, other types of... We'll talk in a minute why it's not
full
חמץ. chametz. But what does הרי הרי, harei harei, we'll talk in
a minute why it's not full חמץ. chametz. But what does הרי
זה עובר בפסח? harei zeh over b'Pesach? So that could just be
a generic phrase leading up to the last line: you transgress. How
do you transgress? You get a לאו, lav, you don't get כרת,
karet, and it's all talking about eating it. Okay. However, רש"י Rashi
says הרי זה עובר בפסח harei zeh over b'Pesach means you transgress
a different prohibition, not the prohibition of eating it. What other prohibition
exists by? By owning it. So רש"י Rashi says הרי זה עובר
harei zeh over means you transgress by owning it and you will
transgress by eating it but not get כרת. karet. That's how רש"י
Rashi reads it. And one of the בעלי תוספות Baalei Tosafot even
goes further to say the language of הרי זה עובר harei zeh
over doesn't mean you transgress, but it means the following must be
removed: אלו עוברים בפסח, eilu ovrim b'Pesach,
you must עובר, over, you must מעביר ma'avir them, you must remove
them, meaning get them out of your house. Okay, but either way
according to that, the reading is that you transgress בל יראה ובל
ימצא. bal yira'eh u'val yimatzeh. רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam disagrees. And רבנו
תם Rabbeinu Tam says you do not transgress בל יראה ובל ימצא
bal yira'eh u'val yimatzeh except for חמץ chametz that you get כרת
karet for. So רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam actually says that all of
this הרי אלו עוברין harei eilu ovrin just means if you eat
it you transgress, but he claims or it means rabbinically you have
to get rid of them. Yes, you get rid of them because
rabbinically we don't let you own them, but according to him you
do not transgress בל יראה ובל ימצא. bal yira'eh u'val yimatzeh. So
again, to repeat the principle of the המשנה, Hamishnah, there's a group
of things that's not full חמץ. chametz. You get a negative prohibition
for eating, you don't get כרת, karet, and you have to get
rid of them. But there's a debate of the ראשונים Rishonim whether
the getting ridding of them is just דרבנן d'rabbanan or is it
even דאורייתא. d'Oraita. Is the biblical בל יראה ובל ימצא bal yira'eh
u'val yimatzeh
limited to חמץ chametz for which you get כרת? karet? That is
a debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Now, why
do you not get כרת, karet, why is this not full חמץ?
chametz? There are basically two or three reasons here. Okay. Reason number
one is some of them are בתערובת, b'ta'aruvet, are in a mixture,
are not straight חמץ. chametz. Now what type of a mixture lowers
it from כרת karet down? I mean other things we say that
if they're in a mixture as long as you get the טעם,
ta'am, it's still the biblical prohibition, or if it's a רוב rov
or whatever. So what type of mixture lowers it from כרת karet
to a לאו? lav? We'll talk about it, but some of these
things obviously are mixtures. Okay. Think about the כותח, kutach, the dip
and other types of things. They have a certain amount of חמץ,
chametz, but not, you know, that's only a minority ingredient. So one
is because it's תערובת. ta'aruvet. Another reason it might not be כרת
karet is because it's a category called חמץ נוקשה. chametz nuksha. Now
חמץ נוקשה chametz nuksha
is a category of something that somehow does not fully become חמץ,
chametz, but it's quasi. I mean it's sort of, I'm not really
explaining it because it's a little tautological here. Okay. But to some
degree maybe the fermenting is not complete. We have to figure out
exactly what חמץ נוקשה chametz nuksha is. The third possibility is that
it's not fully edible. Maybe it's ראוי לכלב ra'ui l'kelev for a
dog to eat but not fit for a person to eat. So
those are three things to factors about why you might not get
כרת: karet: mixture, not fully fermented, and not fully edible. So Michael
asked, what about this paste of the things? So first of all,
maybe paste nowadays you wouldn't eat, but if you made, you know,
when you have Play-Doh or you know, that type of stuff, you
know, you can make homemade Play-Doh which is basically a type of
a dough. You know, so it's possible that some of that stuff
really is edible even though it's primarily used for other types of
purposes. But a lot of these things here, some of the things
in the beginning are foods, but they're not straight חמץ. chametz.
Right, right. Some of the things, but they've got other ingredients in
them. So some
of the stuff in the beginning seems to be more like it
is food but it's תערובת, ta'aruvet, and some of the stuff at
the end is not food. It might be fit for a dog
but not fit for a human or not be fully fermented. So
those are like different types of ways that things can be in
this transgression,
לאו lav but not כרת. karet.
Wait, so if it's not food then why am I עובר over
on it for eating?
Because it might still be fit for a dog and that might
be enough to be to transgress but not enough to get כרת.
karet.
Okay, so that's opposed to let's say then stuff like let's say
medicine which is not food at all, not fit for a dog?
נפסל מאכילת כלב nifsal me'achilat kelev though, that could be different.
Okay, so we'll take a look, let's see as the גמרא Gemara
continues to develop this. Okay, so let's look at the גמרא. Gemara.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. שלשה דברים נאמרו בכותח הבבלי. shlosha d'varim ne'emru
b'kutach habavli. Now we get a chance to describe some of these
things before we get to like the real halachic underlying principles. We
first get to describe the various things mentioned in the
משנה. Mishnah. So there are three things said about this כותח הבבלי:
kutach habavli: מטמטם את הלב, metamtem et halev, it stops up the
heart. It's like got high cholesterol I guess. Anyway, somehow it affects
your heart in a not good way. מסמא את העיניים, mesame et
ha'einayim, blinds the eyes. Apparently רש"י Rashi says because there's a lot
of salt in it and we know the גמרא's Gemara concern about
mineral salt and you wind up touching... get to your eyes ומחליש
את הגוף Umachlish et haguf and generally just weakens the body. מטמטם
את הלב משום נסיובי דחלבא Metamtem et halev mishum nisyubet d'chalba so
it stops up the heart because of the sort of, the sort
of sourdough in it, and not the sourdough, the sour milk in
it, the whey in it, so that's not good for the heart.
ומסמי את העיניים Umasame et ena-im it blinds the eyes משום מלחא
mishum milcha because of the salt in it. ומחליש את הגוף Umachlish
et haguf and generally it weakens the body משום קומניצא mishum kumnitsa
because of קומניצא דאומא kumnitsa d'uma which is the moldy bread that's
in it. Those are the three ingredients basically.
Why did they like to eat it then? Are you kidding me?
It's the McDonald's of their day.
Right, I'm sure it tastes delicious.
Probably was unbelievable.
Exactly. There's this right, this inverse relationship between taste
and whether it's healthy for you. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabanan. שלשה
דברים מרבין את הזבל Shelosha devarim marbin et hazevel there are three
things, three types of food, that increase the excrement, make you excrete
a great
deal וכופין את הקומה Vekofin et hakoma and bend over your stature,
meaning weaken the body ונוטלין אחד מחמש מאות ממאור עיניו של אדם
Venotlin echad mechamesh me-ot mima-or einav shel adam and reduce your eyesight
by one
five-hundredth, by point two percent. אלו הן Elu hen and these are
they: פת קיבר Pat kibar bran bread ושיכר חדש Veshichar chadash and
new beer or mead וירק חי Veyerek chai and raw vegetables. רש"י
Rashi says it's only if you look at the last רש"י, Rashi,
ירק חי Veyerek chai כגון כרישין ובצלין
וחזרין kegon kerishin uvatzalin vechazarin anyway כשאוכלים מהם הרבה תמיד. kshe-ochlin me-hem
harbe tamid. Okay, when you eat too much of them all the
time. So much for vegetarians. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabanan. שלשה דברים
ממעטים את הזבל Shelosha devarim mema-atin et hazevel now three things in
parallel decrease your excrement וזוקפין את הקומה Vezokfin et hakoma cause your
stature to be upright ומאירין את העיניים Ume-irin et ena-im and they
give light to the eyes, so they're very good for you. אלו
הן Elu hen and these are they: פת נקיה Pat neki-a סמניד
samnid fine flour, white bread. White bread. ובשר שמינא Uvasar shamina good
fatty meat ויין ישן Veyayin yashan and good old wine. So there
you go. Live a
long time. Exactly. Oh my gosh. Okay. פת נקיה Pat neki-a white
bread.
The French do love that, that is true, but anyway. דסמידא Desmida
made out of fine flour.
בשר שמינא Basar shamina fatty meat דציפירתא Detzipirta made from a goat
דלא אפתח Delo aftach that had never given birth, so and somehow
that type of meat is particularly fatty and good for you ויין
ישן Veyayin yashan and old wine עתיק עתיקי Atik atiki very old.
רש"י Rashi says three years old. I don't know where he gets
it from. Old wine? I guess yeah, that's true. I've mentioned a
number of times that Chaim Soloveitchik has said that the whole belief
that רש"י Rashi was a winemaker, actually I should mention this because
it's relevant to פסחים, Pesachim, he says the whole belief that רש"י
Rashi was a winemaker comes from one line he writes in one
תשובה teshuvah where he says I have to end this תשובה teshuvah
now because I have to go out and make the wine.
So we assume he was a winemaker. So Chaim Soloveitchik says anybody
who knows anything about winemaking in France in the Middle Ages understands
that there's like one week during the year where like after the
grapes are picked where like they all have to be pressed based
on, you know, whatever, the weather and whatnot, and the entire town
is involved in the making, in the pressing of the grapes and
the making of the wine. He says it would be as if
רש"י Rashi had written on ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, you'll have to
excuse me I have to go out and bake the מצות, matzos,
and we had determined that he was a baker. So that's
what he claims, that there's really no evidence that רש"י Rashi was
a vintner.
Where's that famous article, you know that?
I don't know, I heard that from him בעל פה. ba-al peh.
I don't know, a famous article, it's a long article. Okay anyway,
no it's a תשובה teshuvah of רש"י. Rashi. Anyway, okay. Okay, now
כל מילי דמעלי להאי קשי להאי Kol mili d'ma-ali lehai kashi lehai
any types of foods that are eaten for health purposes, if they're
good for one part of the body, like if they're good for
the heart, they're bad for the eyes ודקשי להאי מעלי להאי Vedekashi
lehai ma-ali lehai and if it's bad for one part of the
body, it's good for another part of the body. Okay, בר Bar
with the one exception of מזנגבילא mizangavila which is generally assumed to
be ginger רטיבתא retivta so moist ginger, not dry ginger ופלפלי אריכתא
Upilpili arichta and long peppers ופת נקיה Upat neki-a and clean bread,
white bread ובשר שמינא Uvasar shamina and as we said, white bread,
fatty meat ויין ישן Veyayin yashan old wine, those five, so now
we've added two, the ginger and the peppers דמעלי לכולי גופא D'ma-ali
lechulei gufa they are just good for the whole body. Okay, so
there you go. Now you know the secret to a long healthy
life. Moving on. שיכר המדיי Shichar Hamadai Median beer דרמו ביה מי
שערי Deramu bei mei se-ori that they use from it barley water.
So again, like they ferment barley as opposed to other mead which
would be made from like date honey, you know וחומץ אדומי Vechometz
Adumi
Edomian vinegar
because normal vinegar would be made out of wine, but this... דשדו
ביה שערי deshadu bei sa'ari would be vinegar that would be made
from barley, fermented barley. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak or whatever, אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, בתחילה
כדיהוו מייתי נסכים מיהודה, Betichila kedehavi mevi'im nesachim miYehuda,
originally when they would bring wine libations from יהודה Yehuda at the
time of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, לא היה יינם של יהודה
מחמיץ. lo haya yeinam shel Yehuda machmitz. The wine was of such
amazing quality that it would never spoil, it would never turn into
vinegar, עד שנותנים לתוכו שעורים. ad shenosnim lisocho se'orim. And
if they wanted to get the wine to become vinegar, they would
have to put in some barley and that would then the chemical
reaction would allow it to spoil and to become vinegar. But on
itself it would never become vinegar. So by the way it does
seem, and also that was the language used before in the גמרא,
Gemara, דשדו ביה, deshadu bei, they added into it, meaning when the
גמרא Gemara before spoke about these, the beer and the vinegar, it
sounds like it was not all out of barley or all out
of, you know, it was not beer made all out of barley
or vinegar made all out of barley. It was these things with
a barley additive, right? If you look at the language before, right?
דרמו ביה מי שערי, Deramu bei mei sa'ari, דשדו ביה שערי. deshadu
bei sa'ari.
So yes, it still had a wine base for the vinegar, or
it still had a date base, date honey base for the beer,
but it also had an additive of the barley. So here we're
saying that the wine was of, used to be of such amazing
quality, it would never turn into vinegar, it would never sour unless
they had put in barley as an additive. וקורין אותו חומץ סתם,
Vekoreinu som chometz stam, and that used to just be called vinegar.
ועכשיו, Ve'achshav, and because that was the, because well we'll see, ועכשיו
ve'achshav now, אין יינם של אדומיים מחמיץ. ein yeinam shel adomim machmitz.
That
the Edomian wine is of this high quality. Nowadays our wine, the
Judean wine, is not of that quality, but the Edomian wine is
of that high quality, and their wine does not become, does not
become
vinegar עד שנותנים לתוכו שעורים ad shenosnim lisocho se'orim until you put
in it barley. וקורין לו חומץ האדומי. Vekoreinu so chometz ha'adomi. And
therefore this vinegar, right now, if we just say חומץ, chometz, we
mean vinegar from straight wine. What's the vinegar of straight wine? That's
נעבעך nebach our wine because now our wine is no longer of
such high quality and it will turn to be vinegar. But the
Edomian wine, that's of really high quality, and there it only becomes
vinegar with barley. So when we refer to a vinegar that has
a barley additive, it's called the Edomian vinegar, because the Judean vinegar
is even without the barley additive. לקיים מה שנאמר, Lekayem mah shene'emar,
to fulfill what is meant in the פסוק, pasuk, אמלאה החרבה. imaleh
hacharava. I will fulfill, I will sort of fill, build up the
destroyed places, the desolate places. אמלאה זו חרבה זו ואם מלאה זו
חרבה זו. Imaleh zu charva zu, ve'imaleh zu charva zu. So this
is referring to a פסוק pasuk that speaks about צור Tzor sort
of saying to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and then God promising that I will
rebuild up the destroyed places of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And the דרשה drasha
in the גמרא Gemara is that צור Tzor is from אדום, Edom,
from Rome, and sees it as, you know, when one rises, the
other falls. So the destruction one will be built up, which is
right now one is built and the other is destroyed, in the
end I'll reverse it. So it used to be that the Judean
wine was of high quality, once the חורבן הבית Churban Habayis happened,
the Judean wine was now of poor quality and it will actually
spoil by itself, and the אדומי Adomi wine was of high quality.
Now I have to say something. The גמרא Gemara here is assuming
that אדום Edom here, אדומי, Adomi, means אדום Edom as in the
country that's on the other side of the Jordan in the תורה,
Torah, which is descendant of עשיו, Esav, which in later rabbinic mindset
gets identified with Rome, because of the עשיו ויעקב Esav veYaakov sort
of, you know, enmity, right? So אדום Edom got mapped onto Rome.
Okay, but so besides that historically אדום Edom wasn't Rome, that's how
it got mapped. But besides which, wasn't Idumaean wine probably does not
mean אדום, Edom, right? Wasn't there a, again I'm not great at
this, Idumaean with an 'i', Idumaean with an 'i' is the area
which, exactly, I was going to say Herod was an Idumaean, and
they were forcefully converted by the חשמונאים. Chashmonaim. Right, and the Idumaeans
were not from אדום, Edom, were they? No, no, they were the
Negev, they were southern Bedouins. Right, right. So probably when it refers
here to Idumaean wine at the time this משנה Mishnah is being
written, there is no אדום, Edom, right? And so this Idumae probably
does not mean אדומי, Adomi, and it refers to, and if you
just think about the ברייתא Braisa we just quoted, the contrast of
Judean and Idumaean are these two regions in Israel. But the גמרא
Gemara now is connecting it to אדום, Edom, which it also identifies
with Rome and seeing this as, oh, it was after the חורבן
הבית, Churban Habayis, so Rome destroyed, our wine went down, and their
wine went up, and that's the one is high and the other
is low. They're thinking ברטנורא Bartenura Italian wine. Yeah. So, רב נחמן
בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak in that general area though, right?
It is, but it's not אדום. Edom. I understand, but it's still...
there's two sort of historical inaccuracies going on here. One is the
general rabbinic mapping of אדום Edom to Rome, and the other is
identifying what in the משנה Mishnah probably is Idumea, or you know,
with אדום. Edom. Okay.
רב נחמן בר יצחק
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak מהכא. meihacha. וללאום מלאום יאמץ, Ule'om mile'om ye'ematz,
right? Which is the prophecy of עשו Esav and יעקב. Yaakov.
One nation will strengthen against the other nation or fight against the
other nation, which means that what one of them, you know, one
of them is always on the top.
So when we're, so when our wine was good theirs was bad,
when ours bad theirs became theirs became good. So why? So normal
vinegar is נעבעך nebech just from straight wine, it's the bad wine.
But Edomian vinegar, that it only became vinegar if you had to
if you added barley to the wine. Okay. תניא, Tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא. Braisa. Now by the way רש"י Rashi says, what
does it have to do when we used to bring נסכים? Nesachim?
So could this mean he's saying at the time of the בית
המקדש? Bais Hamikdash? רש"י Rashi also adds in בזכות bizchus that we
brought the נסכים Nesachim from our wine, that because our wine was
used for נסכים, Nesachim, that's also what, you know, what allowed what,
you know, made merited that it should be of such high quality.
So רש"י Rashi makes it also more intimately connected to the bringing
of the נסכים. Nesachim. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa,
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda,
ביהודה, bi'Yehuda, again, in Judea, בראשונה, berishona, it
used to be, הלוקח חומץ מעם הארץ halokeach chometz me'am ha'aretz אינו
צריך לעשר. eino tzarich le'aser.
If you took חומץ, chometz, if you bought vinegar from a normal
person of the of the field, like you know a you
know a normal, you
know, one of the masses, which we normally suspected were not good
about taking מעשר, ma'aser, but if you bought vinegar you don't have
to take it. Why? מפני שחזקה אינה באה אלא מן התמד. mipnei
she'chazakah einah ba'ah ela min hatemed. Because again, since the wine was
of such high quality, they would never sell vinegar which was out
of wine, straight wine. They would only sell vinegar from תמד. temed.
תמד Temed was after you pressed the grapes to make the wine,
you would submerge the sort of lees in water and make like
a weak sort of grape-flavored water or wine-flavored water and from that
you would make vinegar. So since the vinegar was not would never
be made from the real wine, it would only be made from
this תמד, temed, it wasn't a big deal if you took תרומה
ומעשר trumas u'maiser from it. Presumably you don't have to take תרומה
ומעשר trumas u'maiser from תמד. temed. We'll see in a minute. ועכשיו,
Ve'achshav, now because our wine has gone down in quality, הלוקח חומץ
מעם הארץ halokeach chometz me'am ha'aretz צריך לעשר. tzarich le'aser. You have
to take מעשר, ma'aser, שחזקתו אינה באה אלא מן היין, she'chazakato einah
ba'ah ela min hayayin, because now our vinegar נעבעך nebech comes from
real wine. Same basic point as before. Now the גמרא Gemara now
wants to understand this issue of the תמד. temed. וסבר רב יהודה
תמד לאו בר איסורי הוא? Visavar Rav Yehuda temed lav bar issurei
hu? Does that mean that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda thinks that this
תמד, temed, this water flavored with the grape lees does not have
to take מעשר ma'aser from it? והתנן, Ve'hatnan, we taught in the
משנה, Mishnah, המתמד ונתן מים במידה. hametamed venatan mayim be'middah. If you're
making this תמד, temed, so you put water into this barrel with
like lees of grapes, you know, lees is like the dross of
the grapes in it, ומצא כדי מידתו. umatzah kedei middato. You put
in three ounces of water and you took out three ounces. So
you know in the water you took out, there's just the sort
of flavor of the grapes but there's no of the בעין, be'ein,
because you took out as much as you put in. So what's
the story with that? פטור, Patur, you're exempt from taking תרומה ומעשר.
trumas u'maiser. Basically it's flavored water. It's not seen as grapes or
grape juice, and you don't have to take תרומה ומעשר. trumas u'maiser.
רב יהודה מחייב, Rav Yehuda mechayiv, but רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says
you do have to take, you do have to take תרומה ומעשר.
trumas u'maiser. So how can he say you don't have to worry
about the vinegar, it comes from תמד, temed, if he's the one
who says that you have to take תרומה ומעשר trumas u'maiser from
תמד? temed? So the גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. So
here is what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said. לא נחשדו עמי הארץ
על התמד. lo nechshedu amei ha'aretz al hatemed. He says yeah, yeah,
yeah, you have to take תרומה ומעשר trumas u'maiser from it, but
the stuff is so cheap and of so low quality that we
can assume that even though generally they don't take תרומה ומעשר, trumas
u'maiser, here they'll do it because it's not such a big deal,
it's not such a big loss. So so yes, you can buy
it from them, not because you don't have to take, but you
can assume they have taken it because again it is something of
such low quality. איבעית אימא, I'ba'is eima, if you want you can
do נחשדו, nechshedu, there is a concern that they don't take תרומה
ומעשר trumas u'maiser from this תמד. temed. ולא קשיא, Velo kashya, it's
not a difficulty. הא בדופקא הא בפרפוצני. ha bedofka ha beparputzni. It's
a difference is how you make it. Do you make it by
putting it into the the like shells of the grapes? In that
case it's just getting flavor and it's not really it's not really,
you know, considered to have any juice in it and therefore you
don't have to take תרומה ומעשר trumas u'maiser and that's when he
says you're and that's and then he would agree that you're פטור
patur from תרומה ומעשר. trumas u'maiser. And when does he say you're
מחייב mechayiv in תרומה ומעשר? trumas u'maiser? When you actually like not
just you know when you actually like submerge it in pressed grapes
which have actual like juice, you know, some of the juice is
actually there. So two different ways of making it, one in which
you actually much more sort of submerge it in these, you know,
in these pressed grapes which actually gives more flavor and more juice
and actually would be a case which he would say you'd be
מחייב. mechayiv. Okay, so that's what תוספות Tosafos is concerned, but again,
connects to our point that נעבעך nebach nowadays, after the חורבן הבית,
Churban HaBayis, our wine is not as good as it used to
be. I have to tell over this joke, I know it's a
little corny, but I heard from, from Dr. Nachum Sarna, many עליו
השלום, alav hashalom, you know, many years ago. He said, why is
it that, I told you this before, because why is it that
right that so many Jewish dishes start with like the K sound?
Like you have קניש, knish, and קניידל, kneidel, and קרעפלאך. kreplach. So
he says, you have to understand, at the time of the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we had the most amazing foods, they were מעין
גן עדן, me’ein Gan Eden, and they were called names like nish,
nedel, replach. Says now, after the חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis, נעבעך nebach
it's only קניש, knish, it's קניידל, kneidel, and anyway, whatever, okay, little
corny joke there, move on. Okay, now, זיסום המצרי, Zisom HaMitzri, the
Egyptian זיסום, zisom, which is another type of a mixture or dip.
Dr. Nachum Sarna said he knew fifteen Semitic languages. I know. All
right. So מהי זיסום המצרי? Mai Zisom HaMitzri? What is meant, what
is this Egyptian זיסום? zisom? תני רב יוסף, Tanei Rav Yosef, so
רב יוסף Rav Yosef taught: תילתא שערי, Tilta Sa’ari, a third barley,
ותילתא קורטמי, ve-tilta kurtami, a third saffron is normally how it's interpreted,
ותילתא מילחא, ve-tilta milcha, a third salt. Some type of very serious
dip. So again, by the way, notice that all these things now
are חמץ בתערובת, chametz b’ta’aroves, right? You have the כותח kutach which
has like moldy bread, you have the vinegar and the beer which
have a barley additive but are not all barley, and you've got
this זיסום zisom which is a third of this, of, you know,
this what do you call it? Barley, but two-thirds other things. So
all of this is חמץ בתערובת. chametz b’ta’aroves. רב פפא מפיק שערי
ומעייל חיטי. Rav Pappa mapik sa’ari u-me’ayel chiti. רב פפא Rav Pappa
said, no, not barley, he took out barley and he put in
wheat. So he said wheat was the third additive. וסימנך, ve-simanach, the
way to remember who said what, is סיסני, Sisni, the word סיסני
Sisni which is a name of a vessel, and the double S
sound is, is, is פפא שערי. Pappa Sa’ari. No, יוסף שערי. Yosef
Sa’ari. Right, יוסף שערי. Yosef Sa’ari. Okay, so now, how would you
make it? תרו להו, Taru lehu, you sort of, you soak it,
you immerse, you immerse it. וקלו להו, ve-kalu lehu, and then you,
and then you roast it. וטחני להו, ve-tachni lehu, and you grind
it up. ושתו להו, ve-shasu lehu, and then you drink this stuff.
Now, I don't know how you can drink it, because where's the
liquid component to this? You must be תרו להו taru lehu means
you submerge it in water, but still, there's got to be a
serious water component here too if you're drinking it. Okay. מדבחא ועד
עצרתא. Mi-divcha ve-ad Atzarta. So, and this would be something that people
would drink from פסח Pesach until שבועות. Shavuos. So we know חז"ל
Chazal call, you know, עצרת Atzeres is the rabbinic term for שבועות.
Shavuos. דבחא Divcha is the rabbinic, it means זבח. zevach. So it's
פסח, Pesach, קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay, so people would drink it
from פסח Pesach in the springtime from פסח Pesach to שבועות. Shavuos.
דקמיט מרפי, De-kamit marpi, people that actually had constipation, it would loosen
their bowels. Oh, it's Metamucil. They would take the ground stuff and
make a suspension by adding it to water, and then they would
drink it. Right, but what do you mean? What's Metamucil made out
of? Metamucil is exactly that. It's a high bran content powder that
you add to water. The water doesn't absorb it, so it's floating
around in there in a suspension. Interesting. Interesting. Okay, ושתו, ve-shasu, but
are the saffron and salt relevant for this? I have no idea.
But this is a dry thing, וקלו, ve-kalu, so then they must
have added it to water to drink, and particularly if it's for
constipation. Right, interesting. But now look at the next part of it.
ודרפי מקמיט ליה, ve-darpi makmit leh, and people that had, that had
loose bowels, it would constipate them. So it would do either direction
that you needed. So so much for the Metamucil, it's like, it's
like the joke about, you know, this amazing device called a, a,
what are those things you put hot liquid in? Canteen? No, not
a canteen. You know, the things that keep it hot. Thermos. A
thermos. It keeps hot liquids hot and cold liquids cold, but the
question is, how does it know? So anyway, all right, so this
does the same. So okay, anyway, לחולא ולאישתא ובירא le-chola u-le’ishta u-veira
for a sick person or for a pregnant woman, סכנתא, sakanta, it
would be a danger. So they already had on certain things their,
you know, Surgeon General warnings about pregnant women. All right, and that's
those things. וזומא של צבעים, ve-zoma shel tzava’im, this thing of for
dyers. הכא תרגימו מיא דחיוורא, Hacha targu mu maya de-chivra, white water,
דצבי בהו לאווא de-tzavi behu lava or, which is used somehow in
the dyeing or the, of, of, of. of leather. It's not exactly
clear what this is but anyway somehow the whitening of leather, the
dyeing of leather, some type of a thing. It was some type
of, it doesn't tell you the ingredients, but obviously some type of
thing that had some flour content in it. ואמילן של טבחים, V'amilan
shel tavachim, this thing of butchers, what does that mean? פת צרואה,
Pat tzerua, bread made out of grain שלא הביא שליש, shelo hevi
shlish, that had not ripened, it did not even become a third
ripe. שמניחה פי קדירה, Shemenicha pi kedeira, what do you do with
this dough or this grain? You put it on the sort of
on the lip of the pot where the cover and the, you
know, pot meet, ושואבת הזומא, vesho'evet hazuma, and it absorbs the overflow
of the, the froth of what you're cooking. So that, now that
sounds like if it's פת, pat, it's like not בתערובת. betarovet. So
this you have to figure out another reason why it's not bread.
The other things were תערובת, tarovet, but this might be again, it's
stuff you don't use for eating, so maybe it's not fully edible,
or maybe there's another possibility that it didn't fully ferment. Okay, let's
read another one. וקולן של סופרים, V'kolan shel sofrim, and this glue
of scribes. הכא תרגימו, Hacha targimu, here we interpreted this to be
פרוא דאושכפי, perua de'ushchafi, a type of a glue used by cobblers,
by leatherworkers. So we're going to say in a minute why therefore
does it say scribes? Okay, again, which presumably have some type of
a, of a flour, a wheat, a grain content. ורב שימי מחוזנא,
V'Rav Shimi miChozna, or Rav Shimi from Chozna אמר, amar, says, זה
ציפולן של בנות עשירים, ze tzipulan shel benot ashirim, no, this is
a type of a plaster that would be used like on the
skin, you know, women sometimes put these things on their skin, they
peel it off and so on. So it would be a type
of a plaster that rich, you know, rich women would use שמשיירות
אותו לבנות עניים, shemeshairot oto livenot aniyim, that if they had any
leftover they would give it to the, you know, the daughters of
the poor people, which means the סופרים. sofrim. Who are the poor
people? The scribes. The סופרים sofrim also includes like the חדר cheder
teachers. So you had all these rich people sending their, you know,
hiring חדר cheder teachers for their kids and if they had any
leftover of this plaster they would give it to, you know, you'd
know they'd give it to the scribes, they'd give it to the
חדר cheder teachers so that they could have it for their wives
and daughters. So basically it's a type of a plaster used on
the skin. איני, Eini, is this true? והתני רב חייא, V'hatani Rav
Chiyya, didn't רב חייא Rav Chiyya teach: ארבעה מיני מדינה, Arba'ah minei
medina, there are the first four things in the Mishnah are foods
eaten in the city, meaning like, but they're things that are used
by people like they're foods. ושלשה מיני אומנות, Ushlosha minei omanut, and
the last three are things that are used in, what's the word
here, not craft, but like yeah, some type of right, professional object,
you know, some type of thing that isn't a food but that's
used in, but that's but that's used in some, in right, professional
capacity. There's a word I'm missing here. ואי אמרת, Ve'i amart, anyway,
if you say ציפולן של בנות עשירים, tzipulan shel benot ashirim, that
this last thing is not like a glue used by leatherworkers, but
it's some type of a thing that's put on the skin, it's
a plaster for the skin, מאי מיני אומנות איכא? mai minei omanut
ika? It's not related to a professional use, right? It's just a
home use. It's not a food but it's not the מיני אומנות.
minei omanut. ואלא מאי? Ve'ela mai? So the Gemara says, so what
do you want to say? You don't want to say it's a
plaster for the skin. What do you want to say? פרופה דאושכפי?
Perufa de'ushchafi? You want to say it's a glue used by the
leatherworkers? אמאי קרי ליה קולן של סופרים? Amai karei lei kolan shel
sofrim? Why do they call it the glue of, or whatever the
whatever קולן kolan means, but the קולן kolan of scribes? קולן של
צבעים איבעי ליה, Kolan shel tzavaim ibayei lei, they should have called
it the קולן kolan of the leatherworkers, of the cobblers. אמר רב
אושעיא, Amar Rav Oshaya, לעולם פרופה דאושכפי, le'olam perufa de'ushchafi, yes, it
is what we've been saying. It's glue used by the leatherworkers. So
and that makes it a מיני אומנות, minei omanut, a type of
a thing that's a professional item. So why do they call it,
ומאי קרי ליה קולן של סופרים? umai karei lei kolan shel sofrim?
Why do they call it this? דסופרים נמי מדבקי בהו ניירותיהן. Desofrim
nami madbeki behu niyaroteihen. It's also used by scribes, they use it
as a glue for their, what do you call it, for their
papers, to glue papers together. Maybe it's primarily used by the leatherworkers,
but yes, it's also a glue used by scribes. So just to
remind us where we're at, we have not identified the underlying principle.
But what we have seen is the first four are various food
products. Maybe the last one is a type of a medicine, but
anyway various things that are eaten and food products where the basic
thing seems to be that it's a minority ingredient and therefore it's
not חמץ בעין, chametz be'ein, it's חמץ בתערובת. chametz betarovet. And the
last set of things seem to be that it might actually be
not בתערובת, betarovet, but something that is used, you know, not as
a food. And therefore maybe it's not fully fit for אכילה, achila,
maybe there's another reason it didn't fully ferment. So we're going to
have to identify that last category where it's not בתערובת, betarovet, why
exactly it's not חמץ גמור. chametz gamur. So we will continue with
this tomorrow.